It's the first time I'm seeing you live.
I'm so glad you're here.
Good afternoon,
yeah this thing is bought it will record
our voice lines so yeah this is the thing
I talked about before
yeah okay I can't I was not able to join
the last lesson it was the issue with my
schedule I I screwed it up because of high
dosage of coffee so I didn't sleep the
whole night and that's simple it was the
main reason and and yeah the week was
decent not that much things going on my at
my work I focusing it English learning
trying to do some stuff with my project
and and yeah how how was your week
what well
I you know okay no I haven't seen the new
spider-man but it's kind of a similar
situation for me because I'm not really
enjoying watching movies even at home but
this year with my girlfriend we visited a
lot of movies in cinema and it was much
better than I remembered so yeah I miss it
they if I would provide some more details
from my side I was still were evolving
that thinking process about about how how
should about that process of kind of mock
interviewing mock mock interview in my
project and I think that a simple mock
interview that we had before is the actual
thing because it's really hard to make to
make this dialogue about some project
interactive rather than just a prepared
question so yeah
yeah I like the approach yeah from my side
it almost looks the same what I would do
besides of that is that between the
lessons I have found a few resources a few
websites that provides you a bunch of
questions about a bunch of interview
questions based on the stack you selected
and I I will try to practice it between
the lessons try you some different
questions right to ask it the AI will
review me and we can work around some weak
spots that I will get and we will just
practice it and I will so from my side I
will practice more in tech side in tech
side and in our English classes we will
just improve the way I can answer this
question maybe this is one of the best
approaches
yeah yeah good so yeah no different
service different service some custom one
and they they may be even funnier than
those
I already sharing the screen you can you
can see it wait a second yes yes I have so
you you have to click on the you see all
right I just noticed that this thing
called called in the Russian do you also
have the same Russian name here or it
automatically translate to English oh okay
a little bit mistake from my side okay
okay so I briefly got through through this
module and yeah it covers almost all the
basics let's just get step-by-step and got
all the interesting parts we also can go
out of script easily it's just a template
anyway you
can interrupt me and asking some chance it
will be even better than just listen so
first of all I have wonderful extension
dark reader I really like it my heart my
eyes hurts me with the blue one oh sorry
with the white one let's let's begin with
so basically on most all of these sections
covers the theoretical things and I will
skip this one first of all because this is
a pure theory and secondary because we
already know that there is a NHTML CSS and
JavaScript such a finish our exists so we
can jump straight to the second one and
this second one gives us a little bit more
interesting thing to work with this thing
is f12 the death death tools it exists
across all the browsers and gives us a
life sub sandbox to to work around and
play with some some codes run JavaScript
on flight for example we can
just print W and the good thing is because
JavaScript is a script based language it
means that it runs in the environment you
don't have to compile it in the program it
will run automatically on the flight we
get the output straight after we press
enter and every every project every
comment will work the same way here for
our convenience I will put this in a video
like that so we could and and yeah so
these sections covered the ID the
environment of development an application
in this case it tells us have you used
this one visual studio code visual studio
there is a to sit to face the visual
studio and visual studio code we can the
similar the second one is just lighter
talking from the perspective of a person
that just learning is starting to learn
programming and pick the JavaScript as his
first language it would be it will be
beneficial it will be desirable step to
have a local pet project to train his
programming encoding skills personally I
believe that the best approaches has 90
percent of practice and 10% of theory and
pet project in this case will be a great
opportunity to do such a thing it
hold on a second
compartment you used to work
I kind of missing the meaning of this
question maybe it's because of English
maybe it's because of
all right thank you for providing me the
question in a with a different paraphrase
we will behave based on our goals and
let's say we have a goal to learn
JavaScript and get our first job in this
area in this major in order to know
JavaScript we have to not just read some
docs we have to practice it so we have to
build some actual website and in order to
practice it we can create we can create a
project and in project we can you
mentioned the game called Tetris we can
actually build the Tetris in this web
application in for what we we can do of
course we can build anything so yeah
this question this question covers a
little bit more advanced techniques as a
first project as a first project it will
be it will be good practice to have a
simple one if for example if you go if you
want to I don't know some landing page or
simple maybe with simple interactivity for
for user it will be a good good example
you also so you can split these little
applications separately or keep it in one
but it will be more complex and it
requires better understanding of an
architecture and the tools we use in so
both approaches are valid it depends off
it depends on our goals and our knowledge
all right all right so we can I'm not sure
which approach is the best based on our
context by context I mean it is just we
just primarily talking about JavaScript
we're not actually trying to learn it so
all right
so yeah let's well let's assume we decided
to create a new project and this project
will be which about what about what this
project will be it should be something
something simple something simple
something so
oh okay okay there will be images all
right we created a new folder it's empty
nothing in there but it is just yet so
this is a Visual Studio code oh my god it
was a long time I was here last time and
all right we have to create a basic
structure of our application as we know
every website has an HTML file and this
will be structured the same way it's index
HTML we can do we can do a simple shortcut
to create a basic structure it will be
like that let me actually check which what
is this gender suggesting h1 button script
app okay let's copy the body and paste it
here and also let me increase the font
size how can I do it like that we will
close the agent window it this is a dark
forbidden technology for us for now I'm
thinking which which direction should I go
next so we're trying to build it build an
actual project let's let's let's just go
step by step based on the chat I think
this is a good approach so step two is
create the JavaScript all right yeah I
will not cover the syntax the syntax
because it's you know mostly most time
it's just boring and that it's it's more
interesting to actually type it in
practice it rather than talking about it
so let's get a little bit higher level of
view what what is going on
all right yeah let me cover in a simple
way what is going on here so doc the first
string is is a basic one it exists in
exists in all of the HTML files and none
of the none of the developers writing it
by hand moreover this template also our
days none of the developers writing it by
hand anymore mostly developers writing to
JavaScript rather than HTML the section of
head is representing the title of our
application and some specific data for
some specific subspecific data that we
don't care at this point of development it
just exists and the second the third the
third part the further important part is
our body the body of our application the
whole content the whole thing that we will
see so basically all what we what we seen
is the body and yeah it has a h1 which is
which is a huge title the button which is
a button and this one is a little bit
different the script is is a link to an
another file which is exist in scope of
this application but we don't have it yet
let's create such one yes so let's jump
back to agenda what it should suggest
suggests to us storage boxes it covers how
we can allocate a variable it's about
syntax not that interesting actually just
just a few sentences it covers how we can
allocate a variable in JavaScript there is
a few ways of doing it and yeah okay
I like the question I really like the
question because this this might feel this
might feels it's a simple question but
it's in order to understand how it works
it you have to dig down to much lower
level of how our computer works and how
this specific language works in in
JavaScript let me provide an example so we
will have a graph talk about so in order
to create a variable let's I will create a
person can just describe right now so
there the red theme is a keyword it
represents that it tells the language that
we want to create a variable actually the
second part is a name of a variable so we
can access it later and the third part is
a is the content of this variable it might
be string number boolean values some some
data structure some function etc etc about
your first question that our variables may
may land in local or global global
environment oh it's it's a complicated
thing to answer even it even with my
experience
yeah let's continue so yeah it covers some
variables console log naming rules yeah
there is a there is a different ways of
how we can name a variable but this is not
really interesting part let me cover it
briefly for example it will be better to
grab my actual keyboard and I'm working
with anyway let's use your profile picture
all right so there is a few ways of how we
can name variables in different languages
there is a different conventions of naming
in JavaScript we name a variable that
contains as a few a few a few words each
word starts with the uppercase letter but
for example in in C maybe in C++ the
convention of variables will be a little
bit different if I remember it correctly
it will look like that so each each word
splits by I don't know how this simple
calls this one calls camel case and this
well this one calls snake case it's again
you know it's all about it's all about
syntax it's all about how we should write
a code not actually what we have to write
not the actual part we have to talk about
I think so there are types there are types
all right
we still talking in this section we will
still talk about variables and what type
of data we can store in our variables and
it's a good thing to have some strange
some simple data like string like numbers
like true or false but it's also there is
a lot of cases I would say most of the
cases where we have to use some structures
some more complicated
videos for example let's create something
called catalog and how can I express it
it's not about English it's
okay there is a thing called Excel tables
in Excel you have a you have a grid of
cells and usually when it comes to
creating a table the structure of data
let's say a number a name of product and a
price of this product so we have two
columns two different values the one which
is name of the product represents its
failure and in JavaScript and in many
languages there is a similar mechanism how
we can store such as such a structure for
example let's say we have we have a
product shoes and this product cost cost
us $20 and we have a product steppers
how much $8 yeah this way and this
connection might be any length any length
and it will look like that and that that's
it so if we if you want to get the value
of of shoes for example we will do
something like if you want to lock the
value of shoes it will look like we want
to put a second I'm looking for a word but
I of course we want to access the catalog
variable and then in this in this catalog
you want to access shoes and this way we
will log the the 12th failure which is
number and it's really useful to represent
some complex datas moreover we can we can
put a different this thing called cost
object by the way with this figure it
braces we can even put some things inside
of this object for example a different
object and it will look like the same way
so nest and let's put just the same values
to represent how it will look like and it
is it may look recursive so an object
represents an object and another object
and etc etc and this is the first type of
useful data programmers user uses rapidly
during during the work process there is a
another type of useful useful structure
called a race it's kind of similar to the
first one we just discovered let's
allocate a new variable we will call the
train and in the first one we use figured
braces in this in this case we will use
squared braces the main difference is that
I have provided an example based on Excel
table which has two two columns let's say
but here we have only one column what it
means is that rather than having two
values we will have only one for example
one then the second one already two and
etc the
main difference the main difference is
that the meant the mental model for these
two for example for this one it's really
useful when we know the name of something
and based on this name we wanna we want to
know the value of this thing but this one
in order to use this one we we don't we
cannot we cannot use it the same way
because of the language rules and the
mental model let's it will be trained the
use case for this one is when we know an
order of a thing for example we want to
grab the thing that is on the first place
in programming it works in a little bit in
a weird way for example even that I wrote
one it will not grab this one it will grab
this one because this one has a zero order
but again it's about syntax it doesn't
matter that so yeah the main difference is
that again just repeating that for objects
it's necessary to use when we when we know
names and for arrays it's necessary to use
when we know an order otherwise it's
basically the same thing and before I will
proceed let's let's make it more
discussion like I know it's what might be
hard though to put some questions because
I'm just describing the thing but for
example I don't know talking about
business value this one might be useful
when yeah even with this list you see we
have a structure of paragraphs or sections
and why is it so like it basically a list
of strings and under the hood it is just
this thing representing one by one so can
I can I jump to this yeah for example you
see no e should before us the sound before
something for under the hood it looks like
that and we will in order to render it we
will just add in some syntax syntax fiends
and then we got the list of the sentence
and thank
you it's a little bit harder to provide
you an example of let me scroll down to
our last last thing we were talking about
it's a little bit harder to provide an
example of using this structure because
for this one uses for rendering much
frequently than this one for for some
reasons it doesn't matter this one uses
more frequently for some internal
calculations of back-end responses oh I
know the case maybe maybe maybe maybe
maybe give me a second oh all right okay
let me increase a little bit the scale so
what is going on on the screen right now I
have opened the dev tools of of our
current agenda this is what happens under
the hood and specifically this list of
things I'm on the network tab which is
represents the responses from the back-end
and reminding that we trying to understand
the use case for this structure the
response from the back-end usually comes
in this shape usually comes in this shape
this is array this array oh my god why why
is this a race log log log log okay give
me give me a second maybe maybe this one
will be more useful for us
hello sir it's also in there
I am believing that what what you're
saying it just it's not it's not it's
based on chromium but it's not Google
Chrome browser yeah our agenda is very is
very large 2200 pages this is insanely
huge agenda for some reason in this case
is the responses in array structure not an
object and not the best example but
usually it comes in the in this way anyway
anyway
the next the next
sections telling us about such things like
a numbers booleans these things I think
it's not really necessary to talk about
because again it's purely about syntax
what else can we talk about operation
logic it's also these things that the
other operations are quite the same in not
just every language but it's also the same
as a regular math so so yeah comparison
this is also simple logical operations
logical operations all right I'm trying to
connect a thing with a business case just
to be able to talk about in a bit more
interactive frame
yeah this is a good case actually maybe I
will provide a simple example we can use
both of these structures and these logical
operators the the common case for
businesses is representing some data for a
user for a client usually it's a list of
data maybe tables maybe maybe something
similar like this list in our agenda and
let's assume we just receive received
response from the back end with a raw data
we should represent on the page you know
application for example let's let it be
and because this is a list of data it will
be an array and in case of agenda this
means okay let's say they are simple this
is just strings but if we will try to
represent some table it might be kind more
complicated it might contain a separate
list of different values a list of
different use and so in this case we will
not able to fit everything in one single
type of type of value in this tree in this
case the objects will be really useful for
us because rather than just putting and
get an object and provide for example ID
which will be sounds true we can provide a
name let's let's let's have a better name
of a field that's let's name it client
name it will also get the string value
let's also provide a is active is this
client currently active in our system is
active and and we actually done it's
enough for now and let's say the back-end
gives us just a free items of this data
from the database for a little bit more
convenience let's let's give them some
values client name A, B, C
yes absolutely this is what we're doing
it's also possible to grab some mocked
datas from some services that is on the
internet but in our case it will be more
representative for us and get a step back
in case of is active we wanna this type of
data representing true or false so Boolean
value yes of course and in this case it
will be let's say true here true here and
false here all right and let's now since
we have hard-coded data we want to
actually do something with this data in
order to show it in our application in the
actual world it will require us to grab
some list of extra technologies of extra
tools in order to turn it on and launch
the application but let's keep this thing
simple and add some imagination we will we
want to access the response value and by
response value I mean this array this list
of entities we want to iterate one by one
of these entities in each language is
almost the same way in JavaScript that
there is a using dot notation we can
access specific internal mechanism that is
existing in every single array in every
single this thing and it allows us to move
one element at a time and do something
with this element talking about syntax it
will look something like that so
let's imagine let's imagine this thing
that we just wrote representing some kind
of action that we will do in each
operation and let's say we we want to make
sure that our client that we want to
render only the clients that are active in
our system and just completely disable the
inactive ones the simplest way of doing
that is to check is the active true in
this in all of the languages there is a
thing called conditional structure and
hold on a second how is it
yes you're describing it correctly and
commonly commonly in header server tables
there is a bunch of filters for every
column and yeah we can we can show
anything based on users filters so to
check for example in this case we want to
show again we want to show only the active
clients in order to check it we have to
use another syntax thing based on the
rules of this of this language based based
on specification of JavaScript in order to
have the condition we have to write if and
in round bracers we have to write the
condition itself the simplest way is to
just write is active in this case the
condition also have the body the block of
code that will be executed in case the
condition will be passed the simplest way
is to write it like that but if we will
write it more verbally it will look like
it will look like this so is active
strictly equal to true value and this way
in this scenario we will return a return
means in a iteration we will spit out
thing we working with in this case it's a
user
yeah kinda kinda and here the scenario
when this condition will not be passed
because when we hit this keyword the
iteration will be ended the code will not
follow this block this block here if we
will reach this one so if the condition
will not pass it will means that we got it
we got an inactive client and in this case
we can simply write the similar thing
return but it will return nothing so we
will not render anything and and I just
finished yeah
oh my god
yeah it was like time traveling for me I
think that yeah we we have we have done a
good amount of developing together and
maybe the good the good way of maybe the
next good step will be not not full mock
interview but as you mentioned just some
some some soft alternative of that we can
pick some little bit simple questions and
talk about them maybe I will be even be
able to provide you some examples some
topics yeah
I agree I agree maybe the the best one of
the best approaches where we can get is to
get maybe one one techie question and
there are the others about some behavioral
interview or some business values and high
level of looking at etc I
really appreciate the amount of not not
patience but the amount of focus during
during our my explanation and yeah I also
enjoyed it actually I did it last time a
few years ago by teaching my friend and
yeah all right I will train some take the
questions and do some other stuff and we
will see you
okay we will speak on Tuesday have a great
weekend as well John and yeah see you bye bye